Guide to the Dale B. J. Randall Papers, 1940-2010s RL.00298
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dale B. J. Randall papers
1940-2010s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Randall, Dale B. J.
RL.00298
24 Linear Feet
Dale B.J. Randall (1929-2016) taught in the Duke English Dept. from 1957-1999 and in the Drama Program from 1991-1999. The collection includes material related to both the English Dept. and the Drama Program as well as Randall's scholarly research. Types of material include correspondence, flyers, programs, clippings, and articles. The collection ranges in date from 1940 through the 2010s.
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection are restricted. Restricted items are noted in the container list.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Dale B. J. Randall Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library and University Archives between 1986-2017.
Biographical Note
Dale B.J. Randall earned his B.A. from Western Reserve University in 1951, his M.A. from Rutgers University in 1953, and his Ph.D. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1958. In 1957, he began teaching at Duke University as an Instructor in English, a position he had until 1960 when he was promoted to Assistant Professor. In 1970, he was promoted to Professor of English. He was also appointed Professor of Dramatic Literature in1991 and Professor of the Practice of Drama in 1994.
During his career, he served in several posts for the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies and the Folger Institute of Renaissance and 18th century Studies, as Associate Dean of the Graduate School, and as Chair of the Duke Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies. Additionally, Randall served as Interim Director of the Duke Drama Program (now the Dept. of Theatrical Studies) from 1991-1992, when the Program was close to collapsing. Under his leadership, the Program stabilized. Randall also published several works including The Golden Tapestry: A Critical Survey of Non-Chivalric Spanish Fiction in English Translation, 1543-1657, in 1963, Joseph Conrad and Warrington Dawson: The Record of Friendship, in 1968, Gentle Flame: The Life and Verse of Dudley, Fourth Lord North, and Winter Fruit: English Drama 1642-1660.
Randall retired from Duke University in 1999 and was duly appointed both Professor Emeritus of English and Professor Emeritus of the Practice of Drama. He continued researching various works until at least 2010. Dale Randall died in Durham, NC on July 24, 2016.
Collection Overview
The largest part of the collection contains research material pertaining to Lord North, Joseph Conrad and Warrington Dawson, about whom Randall was writing books. His research files include xerox copies, slides, illustrations and microfilm. There are materials from Randall's time in the Dept. of English, particularly the controversy which occurred in the late 1980s-early 1990s. The controversy boiled down to a debate between traditionalists and revisionists. It made national headlines at the time, and Randall refers to it as "The Troubles." There are also syllabi, examination questions, and non-graded student papers. Additionally, the collection contains material from Randall's time as Chair of the Drama Program and includes correspondence, programs, flyers, and clippings.
Randall's papers also include a copy of the written sexual harassment complaint a student made against an English professor in 1981. This folder is restricted for 70 years.
Both University Archives and Special Collections received material from Professor Randall. The accessions have been merged into the finding aid presented here.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged by accession order.
Related Material
Dept. of English Records
Duke University Archives
Dept. of Theater Studies Records
Duke University Archives
Drama -- Studying and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; English literature -- History and criticism; English literature -- 16th century; English literature -- 17th century -- Study and teaching; Duke University. Department of English; Conrad, Joseph, 1830-1891; Duke University. Department of Theater Studies; Duke University. Department of English -- Faculty; Dawson, Warrington, 1878-1962; Randall, Dale B. J.; North, Dudley North, Baron, 1602-1677.; Duke University. Graduate School
- 1986 Accession
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence between Randall and others who had information on Warrington Dawson and Joseph Conrad. There are also photographs that were to be included in Randall's book, as well as his notes and an original letter from Dawson to Conrad.
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. I, Oct. 1963-Aug. 1964 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. I, Oct. 1963-Aug. 1964 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. II, Jul. 1964-Sep. 1964 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. III, Sep. 1964-Feb.1965 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. IV, Jan. 1965-Jun. 1965 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. V, Jun. 1965-May 1966 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. VI, May 1966-Jul. 1967 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. VII, Aug. 1967-Sep. 1968 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. VIII, Sep. 1968-Nov. 1968 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. IX, Dec. 1968-Apr. 1969 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. X, Apr. 1969-Jun. 1969 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. XI, Jul. 1969-Aug. 1969 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. XII, Aug. 1969-Nov. 1969 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. XIII, Nov. 1969-Apr. 1970 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. XIV, Mar. 1970-May 1972 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. XV, Jan. 1973-Aug. 1974 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, No. XVI, Nov. 1974-Sep. 1985 (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, (A), Duplicated Letters (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, (B), Miscellaneous Duplicated Documents (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, (C), Chronology of Events (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, (D), Interviews (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, (E), Illustrations and Dawson Letter (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, Photographs, No. I (Box 1)
  - Conrad-Dawson, Photographs, No. II (Box 1)
- Accession (2007-0015)
  Includes research material pertaining to Lord North, about whom Randall was writing a book. Types of material include slides, illustrations, and microfilm.
  - Research Material, Undated, (6 Folders) (Box 2)
  - Slides (Box 2)
  - Illustration, Bodleian Library (Box 2)
  - Photocopies, Bates College (Box 2)
  - Dictionary of National Biography (1999) (Box 2)
  - Dudley North's Will (1675) (Box 2)
  - Microfilm (1) Alphonsus Houghton Library (Box 2)
  - Microfilm (2) Light in the Way to Paradise (Box 2)
  - Microfilm (3) A Forest of Varieties (Box 2)
  - North Family: Biographical Binder (3 Folders) (Box 3)
  - North Miscellaneous Binder (2 Folders) (Box 3)
  - Bodleian Library Photographs (Box 4 (oversize))
  - Miscellaneous Research Materials (Box 4 (oversize))
- Accession (UA2003-51)
  Includes material from Randall's time in the Dept. of English, with files on the Folger Institute, the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and Stanley Fish.
  - Duke University Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 1987-1994 (2 folders) [Committee records are restricted for 25 years from date of origin.] (Box 5)
  - Duke-Folger Liaison, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - Folger Fellowship, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Folger Institute, circa late 1970s-1980s (Box 5)
  - Folger Institute, circa 1980s (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Folger Statement, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
  - Proceedings, 1976-1982 (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 1978-1980 (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies: Printed Matter, 1976, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies: Enrollment and Report, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies: Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Renaissance Conference, 1979-2002 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Renaissance Conference, 1988-1994 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Renaissance Conference, 1987-1994 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Stanley Fish, Skip Gates: Clippings and Articles about the English Dept., 1988-1992 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - "The Troubles," 1988 (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Accession (UA2003-55)
  Includes correspondence, programs, flyers and clippings from Randall's time in the Drama Program.
  - Emails, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Emails, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - Emails, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Emails and Drama-related miscellany, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Ball, David, and Drama Faculty, circa early 1990s (Box 6)
  - The Changeling, 2000-2001 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - The Changeling, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Drama Program, 1990-1994 (Box 6)
  - Drama Program, 1992-1996 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Drama Program, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Drama Director Search and Miscellany, circa 1990s (Box 6)
  - Josiah Charles Trent Memorial Foundation, 2000-2001 (Box 6)
  - Simons, Diane, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - World Premieres Festival, 1992 (Box 6)
  - World Premieres, 1994-1995 (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Accession (UA2007-0030)
  Includes material from Randall's time in both the Dept. of English and the Drama Program, such as syllabi and examination questions as well a file on the first sexual harassment suit at Duke, which is restricted for 70 years.
  - American Philosophical Society, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Basset Celebration, 1993, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1989, 1998-2000 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, circa 1999-2006 (Box 6)
  - Crisis at Trinity, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Early Fiction: Syllabi, 1963-1990 (incomplete) (Box 6)
  - Edmond Miller, 1987-1989, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Emails, 2003-2006 (Box 6)
  - English Dept., 1962, 1977, 1998 (Box 6)
  - English Dept. Staff Lists, circa 1965-1994 (Box 6)
  - English Dept. Writing Committee, 1982-1983 [Committee records are restricted for 25 years from date of origin] (Box 6)
  - English 21s: Studies in the Novel, circa 1980s-1994 (Box 7)
  - Executive Committee of the Arts and Sciences Council, 2005-2006 (2 folders) [Committee records are restricted for 25 years from date of origin] (Box 7)
  - Few Federation, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Freshman English, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Joseph A. Porter, 1983-1988 (Box 7)
  - Jim Applewhite, 1988 (Box 7)
  - Kenny Williams, 1993, 2004 (Box 7)
  - Land Resources, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - Last Train to Nibroc, 2000 (Box 7)
  - Laura Kay Fleming: Clippings, 1982, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Magdalen College, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Miscellany, 1984, 1994, 2004 (Box 7)
  - Posing Naked, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Printed Matter, circa 1960-2005 (incomplete) (Box 7)
  - Randy's House, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Robert Frost, circa 1977-1985 (Box 7)
  - Renaissance Prelims, 1940-1941, 2004-2006 (Box 7)
  - Sexual Harassment Suit at Duke, 1981 RESTRICTED until 2051 (Box 7)
  - Ten Poems by Dale Randall, 1988 (Box 7)
- Accession (UA2008-0051)
  Includes more files pertaining the Dept. of English and Drama Program as well as research files. Of note are ungraded student papers. The Dearlove Case folder is restricted as it contains personnel information, and one folder with graded student papers is also restricted per FERPA.
  - Correspondence and Emails, 1958-1959, 1978, 1985, 2007-2008 (Box 7)
  - Dearlove Case, 1981, 1983 RESTRICTED until 2053 (Box 7)
  - Dudley North: Correspondence, No. 1, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - Duke Drama, 1992 (Box 7)
  - English Dept.: Student essays, Syllabi, Exam Questions, circa 1961-2002 (incomplete) (Box 7)
  - Euripides' Helen, translated by Peter Burian, 1999 July (Box 7)
  - Founders' Day Banquet Speech, 2003 April 25 (Box 7)
  - George Clarke, 1998-1999, undated (Box 7)
  - The Golden Tapestry, 1963-1964 (Box 7)
  - Graded Student Papers, 1966, 1979 RESTRICTED PER FERPA (Box 7)
  - Herbert Berry, circa 1981-1986 (Box 7)
  - North Project, circa 1967, 1977 (Box 7)
  - North Project: Xerox copies, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Papers (student produced, no visible grades): written for English 216, 1966 Spring (Box 7)
  - Patient on the Table, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Printed Matter: Flyers, Reviews, Playbills, etc., circa 1980s-2007 (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous publications and oversize material, including a movie poster for Much Ado About Nothing (Box 8)
- Accession (2009-0238), 4 boxes
  Files and research materials collected from Randall's office.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  This accession is closed until processing
  - Office files (Box 9-12)
- Accession (2010-0032), 1 box
  Includes research materials relating to Randall's research and writings on Robert James Coffey.
  - Coffey correspondence (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Coffey pictures (Box 13)
  - Robert J. Coffey First Scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Robert J. Coffey Transcript of First Scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Robert J. Coffey Second Scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Robert J. Coffey Transcript of Second Scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Robert J. Coffey Third Scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Robert James Coffey (1839-1910): An Unsung Pennsylvanian Soldier and Writer, published in Cumberland County History, volume 21 (2004), pages 3-15 (Box 13)
  - 'Oh! Yankee Soldier, Spare My Home!': The Wartime Rhymes of Robert James Coffey (1839-1910), published in Studies in American Culture, 31.1 (October, 2008), pages 1-31 (Box 13)
- Accession UA2009-0014, 2 boxes
  This accession is closed until processing. May include restricted material.
  - Loose materials, printed material, Arts & Sciences Council files, 1958 dissertation, correspondence, research files (Box 14-15)
- Accession 2012-0091, 4 boxes
  This accession needs to be reviewed before patrons can access it because it may include restricted material. Contact Rubenstein Library in advance before visiting to use this material.
  Correspondence, family history and genealogy materials, and some Duke departmental materials.
  - Correspondence, 1951-1954, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1971 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1990s (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 2000s (Box 16)
  - Randall family Christmas letters, 1990s-2000s (Box 17)
  - Christmas cards, 1990s, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Early writings, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Soliloquy of a Farmer's Wife, notes, publicity, etc. (Box 17)
  - Grandmother's diary and letters, used for Soliloquy of a Farmer's Wife (Box 17)
  - Family history materials: obituaries, genealogy, photographs, 7 folders (Box 18)
  - Cleveland Heights High School (Box 19)
  - Duke Players (Box 19)
  - Duke Chi Psi fraternity (Box 19)
  - Duke Arts and Sciences Council (Box 19)
  - Duke English and Drama Dept. materials (Box 19)
  - Duke retirement (Box 19)
  - Lettie Randall materials (Box 19)
  - Phyllis Randall materials (Box 19)
  - Frances Randall materials (Box 19)
  - Kenneth Randall materials (Box 19)
  - Bulletins and programs (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 19)
- Accession 2017-0176
  Scope and Contents
  Randall's research materials and printouts from his working editing Cervantes and A Soliloquy of a Farmer's Wife.
  - Cervantes, 2010s
    - Black Characters, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Carrizales, Felipe, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Cervantes, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Charles Blount, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Cuckolds, 2010s; 7 Files (Box 20)
    - Deism, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Edward Blount, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Ending Story, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Estremadura, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Gardia de Loaysa, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Indies, New Spain, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Jealousy, 2010s; 2 Files (Box 20)
    - Leonora, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Mabbe Version, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Music, 2010s (Box 20)
    - "New" (Dale's), 2010s (Box 20)
    - Peru, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Pharamacy- Misc., 2010s (Box 20)
    - Pleadards, re: Blounts, 2010s (Box 20)
    - Seville, 2010s (Box 21)
    - Sir Henry Blount, 2010s (Box 21)
    - Slaves and Harems, 2010s (Box 21)
    - Spanish Language in England, 2010s (Box 21)
    - Thomas Blount, 2010s (Box 21)
    - Women/Virginity, 2010s (Box 21)
    - 2 Versions, 2010s (Box 21)
  - Soliloquy of a Farmer's Wife, 1998-2008
    - Soliloquy Correspondence No. 3, 1998-2008; 4 Files (Box 21, Box 22)
    - Soliloquy Correspondence No. 4, 1999-2006; 2 Files (Box 22)
- Accession 2018-0090
  - France, Erik correspondence, 1991-1995 (Box 22)